JAY CULLIGAN +1.818.699,2551

### linkedin.com/in/jay-culligan

jculligan@gmail.com

## **SUMMARY**

Experienced data scientist with a passion for using practical approaches with machine learning, statistics, and experimentation to solve and prevent business and client problems. Life-long learner excited by challenges and driven by curiosity to measure the unmeasurable. Storyteller translating complex concepts into clear and accessible terms and bringing data to life through visualizations.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Cequence Security, Sunnyvale, CA, USA

Jan 2019 - Present

#### **Data Scientist**

- Increased malicious botnet detection for Cequence's Bot Mitigation SaaS Platform by an average of 20% per client, using a range of rules and machine learning pipelines on HTTP request data.
- Lead the response to multiple web application attacks, working closely with external engineering and security teams increasing Cequence's CQ-AI consultancy and threat reporting services annual revenue by \$600K+.
- Reverse engineered multiple account takeover, web scraping, gift card fraud, and credit card rotation attacks and successfully implemented them on test and production servers.

### Insight Data Science, San Francisco, CA, USA

Sep 2018 - Dec 2018

#### **Data Science Fellow**

- Developed a web-app using natural language processing to generate history podcast recommendations.
- Built a pipeline using Word2Vec to find content based on semantic similarity to user-inputted text.

Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology, Onna, Okinawa, Japan

Nov 2017 - Aug 2018

### Postdoctoral Scholar

- Applied neural network classifiers to investigate the color-changing capabilities of cuttlefish.
- Used Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) to model camouflage adaptation to diverse environments based on predator visual capabilities.

## University of Sussex, Brighton, East Sussex, UK

Sep 2013 - Oct 2017

#### **Postgraduate Researcher**

- Conducted a range of experiments using digital image analysis, inferential statistics, as well as unsupervised and supervised models to investigate the visual and rapid camouflage capabilities of cephalopod species.
- Used logistic regression classification on Gabor filter outputs of cephalopod images, tuned to predator visual capabilities, to support theories on disruptive camouflage.
- Applied Gaussian Mixture Models (GMMs) with Principal Components Analysis (PCA) on scored images of cephalopod camouflage patterns to suggest cephalopod patterning is continuous, not discrete.

# **EDUCATION**

PhD, Biology, University of Sussex

2017

Bachelors, Biology, Minor in Psychology, Indiana University

2013

# **LANGUAGES & FRAMEWORKS**

Python SQL MATLAB Java\* Scala\* Javascript\* | AWS H2O Spark Git Docker Jupyter VSCode \*indicates familiarity